This task is about to reachability graph of
a Petri Net and we have been given a Petri
Net and we shall create the reachability graph
for it.
So, this leads us to our first task which
is determining the initial marking.
So, first of all, we look at all the places
and we see that in S1 there are two tokens
and in S2, S3 and S4 there are zero tokens.
And this is our initial state and if we write
down the states and given the order of these
places, we define the place order for
this graph as being place one being
S1, the second position being place S2 and
the third position being S3 has zero tokens
and the fourth position being place four having
zero tokens.
And we keep this sequence for the complete
reachability graph.
And because this is the initial state, we’ll
require an arrow going to the initial state,
so, like this.
And this marks it as the initial set having
an arrow going there.
This is important to have, so, this is the
initial marking.
And now, we can think of how to get to the
next state.
And this is considering the graph here, the
Petri net and we have to think of all the
transitions that are active.
And T4 is not active, because there are no
tokens in S4, T3 is not active, because there
are no tokens in S3, S2 is not active because
there are no tokens in S2.
So it's only T1 that we can fire because there
are tokens in S1.
So we can fire T1 and this would lead to a
new state.
So this is the new marking we get and we can
name this marking here.
So, first of all, we can check that we have
this marking not named yet.
But there's one token in S1 and we have
no state referring to that marking.
So that's why we create a new state, one token
for S2 and S3 and S4 have zero tokens.
So this is our new state.
And we have a transition going from the initial
state to this new state via firing transition
T1.
So okay, then we continue with this state.
So now we have two options, we can either
fire T1 again.
So if we do this,
then we get another token in S2, so we again,
check, have we got this state already in our
reachability graph?
And we see zero tokens in S1, we don't have
this yet, so we create a new state.
And we have zero tokens in S1 and two tokens
in S2 and zero and S3 and zero in S4 and we
reach this state, by firing
T1.
So this is the sequence that leads us into
this state.
And when we consider this state now, then
we don't have any option of firing another
transition because there's none active.
T4 and T3 require a token in S4 or S3 respectively
and transition T1 requires a token in S1 and
T2 requires not only a token in S2, but also
a token in S1.
So, have to get back to this state here so,
let's go back.
And when we are in this state, then we have
not only the option to fire T1, as we already
did, but we can also fire T2.
So, this is what we can do now.
So we fire T2, we get a new token in S3 then
there is no token in S2 anymore, but also
the tokens in S1 are gone.
Again, we check if this is a new state.
No tokens in S1 and no tokens in S2, we don't
have yet a state with that label, which means
we can create a new state.
And it's zero tokens in S1, zero tokens in
S2, and one token in S3.
And this was using this transition here
by using transition 2.
Now that we've reached this state here, we
can fire another transition, and this is T3.
We cannot fire T2, we cannot fire T1 and we
cannot fire T4 each because there are no tokens
in the required places but we can fire T3
and this will lead to a new state.
We remove the token of S3 and we get one token
in S4.
And we get one token back in S1.
So this again is a new state, we have no state
yet where there is a token in S4, that's why
create a new state.
And there are zero tokens in S3, there is
one token in S4 and there's one token
in S1, and zero tokens there in S2.
And we reached this state by firing T3.
Now that
we've reached this marking, we have got two
options.
So we can't fire T3 because there are no tokens
in S3 and we can't fire T2 because there are
no tokens in S2.
But we can fire either T4 or we can fire T1.
So let's first of all fire T4.
So if we do that, then we remove one token from
S4 and get one token in S1.
And now we have to check if this is a state
that we've covered already but as we can see
the graph is now original, we now
have two tokens in S1, we have zero tokens
in S2, zero tokens in S3, and zero tokens
in S4.
So we create no new state, but
we add in a transition, which goes from this
state to the state that we just reached by
firing T4.
And as we haven't covered all the states that
we can reach from this marking,
we go back to the marking.
So once more, we go back to this state, this
marking where we have one token in S1 and
one token in S4.
And in the reachability graph, we can add
another edge going to a state where we actually
fire T1.
So, if we fire T one, we will remove one token
in S1 and add a token in S2 and this is a
new state.
So now we have one token
in S2, we have zero tokens in S1, we have
one token in S2, and we have one token in
S4, and we got there by firing T1.
So that's the label of the edge.
And now that we are in this state, we can
fire T4 once more.
We can't fire any other transition because
there are no tokens in S1 and because there
are no tokens in S3.
So that's why we can't fire T2 and we can't
fire T3 and we can't fire T1.
So we can only fire T4.
And when we do that, we remove one token from
S4 and add a token in S1.
And now we have got a marking where there
is one token in S1 and one token in S2 and
all the others have zero tokens.
When we look at our graph, we see that there
is already a state describing exactly this,
and this is this state here.
So we add this edge here, maybe make the graph
a bit more readable by putting it like this.
This was reached by actually firing T4.
So we fire T4 and get back to this state.
And from there, we can continue as mentioned
before.
Now, as we have considered all the states
already with all the transitions, we have
finally reached a state where we have got
the complete reachability graph.
And so we have covered every connection and
every state.
And so the take away for creating the reachability
graph, it's really important to consider every
state and consider every transition.
And when you add a new state, check before
if the state already exists.
And if it exists, add an edge going to the
existing state and only if it doesn't exist,
create a new state.
And that's it for this task.